# RAHUL SINGH

## rahulsingh2240@gmail.com · +91 9873603841 · rahul2240@github.io

#### **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY**

Dedicated Software Engineer with almost 4 years of full time experience in **backend development**, specializing in Node.js — C++. I'm dedicated to mastering architecture design and coding best practices, with experience in both independent and team-based roles.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

### SOFTWARE ENGINEER 3 AT ROOTER (India's Leading Game Streaming Platform) January 2022-Present

- **Developed** from scratch rest API for an **e-commerce** platform, where sellers can sell digital, physical, and real-time top-ups in their gaming accounts on steam, BGMI, Free Fire along with **payment gateways** such as Paytm and Razorpay and added support for refunds, tracking delivery, wishlist items, and many more features.
- **Developed** from scratch an in-app notification tab to update users with must-watch content, profile stats, and updates that lead to **20% increase** in user retention. Used by **7 Million** users per day.
- Integrating ProxySQL over MySql RDS instance to monitor requests by different services, balance the load across replicas, and free up master for writes only. Shifting database to MongoDB overnight to smoothly host India's biggest esports BGMI event with almost 300K concurrent users watching, commenting, and liking the stream.
- Developed a user and streamer score calculation pipeline that populates the recommended content on the feed for over 1M users based on the user impressions data. Data was collected from the AWS S3 bucket and was processed on AWS EMR machines and saved to the Redis Database.
- Managing data pipelines that include data transfer (100s of GBs) from sources like Kafka, MySql and mongoDb to S3 via EMR jobs and DMS tasks, where it is used at redshift, quicksight, and ML pipeline.
- Started my journey here with deploying services to Kubernetes from ec2 code deploy that includes adding docker, CI/CD, monitoring on Grafana and autoscaling pods instead of instances leading to 20% cost optimzation of EC2.

#### SOFTWARE ENGINEER AT GRADEUP (Leading Exam Preparation Platform) May 2020-December 2021

- **Revamped** an old **content sharing platform** for freelancers and content writers to share content with the team leading to **70% decreased** response time as p95 went from 1 second to 300ms and reduced error rate by 50%.
- Implemented searching using ElasticSearch on the main Byjus Exam Prep website for users to search for videos, live sessions and content.
- Implemented automatic sitemap generation using messaging queues and REST API architecture leading to 300% more content in sitemap and brought the content to top 5 on search results in Google search.
- Trained a Deep Learning Model using TensorFlow Library and Python to detect profanity in an image and removed 93% spam profiles.

#### **GOOGLE SUMMER OF CODE 2019**

May 2019-Sept 2019

- Selected as 1 of 2 participants out of 50+ candidates for the 3 months internship for designing and developing an invitation system in Open Source Event Manager for openSUSE organization.
- My task was to understand the existing codebase, design the APIs, build the user interface, and write the tests for the complete module with 90% test coverage.

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming Language: C++, Javascript, Python, Go
- Programming Frameworks: ExpressJS, NestJs
- Database: MySQL, PostgresSQL, Cassandra, DynamoDB, MongoDb
- **DevOps:** Git, Docker, Kubernetes, CI/CD
- Data: DMS, Redshift, Quicksight, Hadoop
- Other Technologies: SQS, Redis, Kafka

## **PROFILE LINKS**

LINKEDIN: rahul2240GITHUB: rahul2240LEETCODE: rahul2240

## **ACHIEVEMENTS**

#### 1. MENTOR IN GOOGLE SUMMER OF CODE 2023

April 2023

Mentoring eval.ai open source platform where people hosts machine learning contests.

#### 2. WINNER SMART INDIA HACKATHON

Aug 2020

Won **1st place** out of **50+ teams** nationwide. Developed a negotiation portal for government officials that includes **rich text editor with real time collaboration** of users along with **video chat** functionality.

## 3. GOOGLE CODE IN 2019, TENSORFLOW

Dec 2019

Mentored school students and helped them in contributing to open source projects such as TensorFlow.

## 4. PUBLICATION BREAST CANCER DETECTION

Nov 2020

Breast Cancer Classification Using Transfer Learning in LNEE, Springer, 2020.

#### **EDUCATION**

## JSS Academy Of Techincal Education, Noida

2016 - 2020

Bachelor of Engineering in Information Technology. CGPA: 8.03/10.00